<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<PRONOM-Report xmlns="http://pronom.nationalarchives.gov.uk">
  <report_format_detail>
    <FileFormat>
      <FormatID>1959</FormatID>
      <FormatName>Markdown</FormatName>
      <FormatVersion>
      </FormatVersion>
      <FormatAliases>
      </FormatAliases>
      <FormatFamilies>
      </FormatFamilies>
      <FormatTypes>Text (Mark-up)</FormatTypes>
      <FormatDisclosure>
      </FormatDisclosure>
      <FormatDescription>Markdown was created by John Gruber and Aaron Swartz circa 2004. The purpose of Markdown is to let users write clean text-based documents that do not suffer from the legibility issues of other 'markup' formats. 

Markdown uses combinations of characters, for example, hashes (pound-sign), asterisks, and combination of square- and rounded- brackets to prefix or suffix parts of text. The symbols provide instructions to an interpreter. A single hash '#' for example, that prefixes a line of text is an instruction to make that line a top-level header in a formatted document. Two hashes '##' is an instruction to render, or output, a secondary header. And so on.

Ultimately the result of writing markdown is a document that can be parsed into a well-formed version of other presentation languages such as HTML or XHTML.

There is no single specification for Markdown, nor is there a single canonical output. That is, Markdown syntax could be converted into many other file types. 

Further descriptions of the background of Markdown and a list of Markdown 'flavors' can be found on the Archiveteam Just Solve It File Formats Wiki: http://fileformats.archiveteam.org/wiki/Markdown

Wikipedia also provides a thorough description of Markdown and its syntax: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown#Standardization</FormatDescription>
      <BinaryFileFormat>
      </BinaryFileFormat>
      <ByteOrders>
      </ByteOrders>
      <ReleaseDate>
      </ReleaseDate>
      <WithdrawnDate>
      </WithdrawnDate>
      <ProvenanceSourceID>195</ProvenanceSourceID>
      <ProvenanceName>Artefactual Systems Inc / Artefactual Systems Inc</ProvenanceName>
      <ProvenanceSourceDate>23 Jul 2018</ProvenanceSourceDate>
      <ProvenanceDescription>
      </ProvenanceDescription>
      <LastUpdatedDate>23 Jul 2018</LastUpdatedDate>
      <FormatNote>
      </FormatNote>
      <FormatRisk>
      </FormatRisk>
      <TechnicalEnvironment>
      </TechnicalEnvironment>
      <FileFormatIdentifier>
        <Identifier>fmt/1149</Identifier>
        <IdentifierType>PUID</IdentifierType>
      </FileFormatIdentifier>
      <FileFormatIdentifier>
        <Identifier>text/markdown</Identifier>
        <IdentifierType>MIME</IdentifierType>
      </FileFormatIdentifier>
      <ExternalSignature>
        <ExternalSignatureID>2175</ExternalSignatureID>
        <Signature>md</Signature>
        <SignatureType>File extension</SignatureType>
      </ExternalSignature>
    </FileFormat>
    <SearchCriteria>Criteria</SearchCriteria>
  </report_format_detail>
</PRONOM-Report>
