<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<PRONOM-Report xmlns="http://pronom.nationalarchives.gov.uk">
  <report_format_detail>
    <FileFormat>
      <FormatID>800</FormatID>
      <FormatName>Batch file (executable)</FormatName>
      <FormatVersion>
      </FormatVersion>
      <FormatAliases>
      </FormatAliases>
      <FormatFamilies>
      </FormatFamilies>
      <FormatTypes>Text (Structured)</FormatTypes>
      <FormatDisclosure>
      </FormatDisclosure>
      <FormatDescription>A Batch file is a scripting language native to MS-DOS, Microsoft Windows, and formerly OS/2. Scripting allows users to chain commands that are available to an operating system together to complete a set of tasks. Scripting provides the means to save the commands required for repetetive tasks and use them over and over again. Batch files are written as plain-text and so can potentially be understood by anyone opening these in a plain-text editor. Commands can range from operating system specific commands to command-line applications installed by the user. The existence of variables, loops, and conditional statements means that batch files can be fairly complex in their operation and may take some understanding to understand exactly what they're doing. In the case of receiving legacy Batch files into an archive, commands may no longer be accessible, breaking parts of a batch file useless. Users might want to be wary about executing batch files outside of a boxelsboxed environment. Comments are marked with 'Rem' ('remark') and may help users to decode what a script is doing. A script will usually begin with the command '@echo off' which prevents all commands from being printed to the screen during the course of a script's execution but can be switched on again as necessary to help with debugging. Batch file syntax can still be learned and understood, for example from sites such as Tutorialspoint: https://www.tutorialspoint.com/batch_script/index.htm</FormatDescription>
      <BinaryFileFormat>Text</BinaryFileFormat>
      <ByteOrders>
      </ByteOrders>
      <ReleaseDate>
      </ReleaseDate>
      <WithdrawnDate>
      </WithdrawnDate>
      <ProvenanceSourceID>1</ProvenanceSourceID>
      <ProvenanceName>Digital Preservation Department / The National Archives</ProvenanceName>
      <ProvenanceSourceDate>02 Feb 2007</ProvenanceSourceDate>
      <ProvenanceDescription>04/2024 (v.118)- Description added. Submitted by Ross Spencer as part of PRONOM Research Week 2023.</ProvenanceDescription>
      <LastUpdatedDate>15 Apr 2024</LastUpdatedDate>
      <FormatNote>https://www.tutorialspoint.com/batch_script/index.htm</FormatNote>
      <FormatRisk>
      </FormatRisk>
      <TechnicalEnvironment>
      </TechnicalEnvironment>
      <FileFormatIdentifier>
        <Identifier>x-fmt/413</Identifier>
        <IdentifierType>PUID</IdentifierType>
      </FileFormatIdentifier>
      <ExternalSignature>
        <ExternalSignatureID>806</ExternalSignatureID>
        <Signature>bat</Signature>
        <SignatureType>File extension</SignatureType>
      </ExternalSignature>
    </FileFormat>
    <SearchCriteria>Criteria</SearchCriteria>
  </report_format_detail>
</PRONOM-Report>
